Chapter 31 My home then, when I at last find a home, is a cottage.
A little room with white washed walls and a sanded floor containing four painted
chairs and a table, a clock, a cupboard, with two or three plates and dishes,
and a set of tea-things in Delph.
Above, a chamber of the same dimensions as the kitchen, with a deal bedstead and
chest of drawers, small, yet too large to be filled with my scanty wardrobe.
Though the kindness of my gentle and generous friends has increased that by a
modest stock of such things as our necessary.
It is evening.
I have dismissed, with the fee of an orange,
the little orphan who serves me as a handmaid.
I am sitting alone on the hearth.
This morning, the village school opened.
I had twenty scholars, but three of the number can read, none right or cipher,
several knit, and a few so a little.
They speak with the broadest accent of the district.
At present, they and I have a difficulty in understanding each other's language.
Some of them are unmanaged, rough, intractable, as well as ignorant,
but others are docile, have a wish to learn,
and events are disposition that pleases me.
I must not forget that these coarsely clad little peasants are
a flesh and blood as good as the science of gentlest genealogy.
And that the germs of native excellence, refinement, intelligence, kind feeling are
as likely to exist in their hearts as in those of the best born.
My duty will be to develop these germs.
Surely, I shall find some happiness in discharging that office.
Much enjoyment I do not expect in the life opening before me, yet it will doubtless
if I regulate my mind and exert my powers as I
ought, yield me enough to live on from day to day.
Was I very gleeful, settled, content, during the hours I passed in Yonder Bayer
humble schoolroom this morning and afternoon?
Not to deceive myself, I must reply.
No, I felt desolate to a degree, I felt, yes, idiot that I am, I felt degraded.
I doubted I had taken a step which sank instead
of raising me in the scale of social existence.
I was weakly dismayed at the ignorance, the poverty, the coarseness of all I heard
and saw around me, but let me not hate and
despise myself too much for these feelings.
I know them to be wrong, that is a great step gained.
I shall strive to overcome them.
Tomorrow I trust, I shall get the better of them partially.
And in a few weeks perhaps, they will be quite subdued.
In a few months, it is possible, the happiness of seeing progress and a
change for the better in my scholars may substitute gratification for disgust.
Meantime, let me ask myself one question, which is better?
To have surrendered to temptation, listened to passion, made no painful
effort, no struggle, but to have sunk down in the silken snare, fallen asleep on the
flowers covering it, wakened in a southern climb amongst the luxuries of a pleasure
villa, to have been now living in France, Mr. Rochester's mistress, delirious,
with his love half my time, for he would, oh yes, he would have loved me well for a
while, he did love me, no one will ever love me so again.
I shall never more know the sweet homage given to beauty, youth, and grace,
for never do anyone else shall I seem to possess these charms.
He was fond and proud of me, it is what no man besides will ever be.
But where am I wondering, and what am I saying, and above all, feeling?
Whether is it better, I ask, to be a slave in a fool's paradise at Marseille,
fervored with delusive bliss one hour, suffocating with the bitterest tears of
remorse and shame the next, or to be a village school mistress, free and honest,
in a breezy mountain nook in the heart of England?
Yes, I feel now that I was right when I adhered to principle and law, and scorned
and crushed the insane promptings of a frenzied moment.
God directed me to a correct choice, I thank his providence for the guidance.
Having brought my even-tied musings to this point, I rose, went to my door,
and looked at the sunset of the harvest day, and at the quiet fields before my
cottage, which, with the school, was distant half a mile from the village.
The birds were singing their last strains.
The air was mild, the dew was barm.
While I looked, I thought myself happy, and was surprised to find myself air-long
weeping, and why, for the doom which had left me from adhesion to my master,
for him I was no more to see, for the desperate grief and fatal fury,
consequences of my departure, which might now perhaps be dragging him from the path
of right, too far to leave hope of ultimate restoration, thither.
At this thought, I turned my face aside from the
lovely sky of Eve, and lonely veil of Morton.
I say lonely.
For in that bend of it visible to me, there was no building apparent,
save the church and the passing-age, half-hidden trees, and, quite at the
extremity, the roof of veil hall, where the rich Mr. Oliver and his daughter lived.
I hid my eyes, and lent my head against the stone frame of my door.
But soon, a slight noise near the wicket which shut in my
tiny garden from the meadow beyond, it made me look up.
A dog, old Carlo, Mr. Rivers' pointer, as I saw in a moment, was pushing the gate
with his nose, and singin' himself lent upon it with folded arms.
His brown knit, his gaze, grave almost to displeasure, fixed on me.
I asked him to come in.
No, I cannot stay.
I have only brought you a little parcel my sisters left for you.
I think it contains a color box, pencils and paper.
I approached to take it.
A welcome gift it was.
He examined my face, I thought, with austerity, as I came near.
The traces of tears were doubtless, very visible upon it.
Have you found your first day's work harder than you expected?
He asked.
Oh no, on the contrary, I think in time I shall get on with my scholars very well.
But perhaps your accommodations, your cottage, your
furniture, have disappointed your expectations.
They are in truth scanty enough, but I interrupted.
My cottage is clean and weatherproof, my furniture sufficient and commodious.
All I see has made me thankful, not despondent.
I am not absolutely such a fool and sensualist, as to
regret the absence of a carpet, a sofa and silver plate.
Besides, five weeks ago, I had nothing.
I was an outcast, a beggar, a vagrant.
Now I have acquaintance, a home, a business.
I wonder at the goodness of God, the generosity of
my friends, the bounty of my lot, I do not repine.
But you feel solitude and oppression.
The little house there behind you is dark and empty.
I have hardly had time yet to enjoy a sense of tranquility,
much less to grow impatient under one of loneliness.
Very well.
I hope you feel the content you express.
At any rate, your good sense will tell you that it is too
soon yet to yield to the vacillating fears of Lot's wife.
What you had left before I saw you, of course I do not know.
But I counsel you to resist firmly every temptation, which would incline you to
look back, pursue your present career steadily, for some months at least.
It is what I mean to do, I answered.
Shingin continued, it is hard work to control the workings of inclination and
turn the bent of nature, but that it may be done, I know from experience.
God has given us, in a measure, the power to make our own fate,
and when our energies seem to demand a sustenance they cannot get, when our will
strains after a path we may not follow, we need neither
starve from inclination nor stand still in despair.
We have but to seek another nourishment for the mind, as strong as the forbidden
food it long to taste, and perhaps pure, and to hue out for the adventurous foot,
a road as direct and broad as the one fortune has blocked up against us,
if rougher than it.
A year ago, I was myself intensely miserable, because I
thought I had made a mistake in entering the ministry.
Its uniform duties weird me to death.
I burnt for the more active life of the world, for the more exciting toils of a
literary career, for the destiny of an artist, author, orator, anything,
rather than that of a priest.
Yes, the heart of a politician, of a soldier, of a votary of glory,
a lover of renown, a lustre after power, beat under my curate surplus.
I considered.
My life was so wretched, it must be changed, or I must die.
After a season of darkness and struggling, light broke and relief fell.
My cramped existence all at once spread out to a plane without bounds.
My powers heard a call from heaven to rise.
Gather their full strength, spread their wings, and mount beyond ken.
God had an errand for me.
To bear which afar, to deliver it well, skill and strength, courage and eloquence.
The best qualifications of soldier, statesmen, and orator were all needed,
for these all center in the good missionary.
A missionary I resolved to be.
From that moment, my state of mind changed, the fetters dissolved and dropped
from every faculty, leaving nothing of bondage
but its galling sawness which time only can heal.
My father, indeed, imposed the determination.
But since his death, I have not a legitimate obstacle to contend with.
Some affairs settled, a successor for Morton provided, an entanglement or two of
the feelings broken through or cut us under.
A last conflict with human weakness, in which I know I shall overcome,
because I have vowed that I will overcome.
And I leave Europe for the East.
He said this, in his peculiar subdued yet emphatic voice, looking when he had ceased
speaking not at me, but at the setting sun at which I looked too.
Both he and I had our backs towards the path leading up the field to the wicked.
We had heard no step on that grass-grown track.
The water running in the veil was the one lulling sound of the hour and scene.
We might well then start, when a gay voice, sweet as a silver bell exclaimed.
Good evening, Mr. Rivers.
And good evening, old Carlo.
Your dog is quicker to recognize his friends than you are, sir.
He pricked his ears and wagged his tail when I was at the bottom of the field,
and you have your back towards me now.
It was true.
Though Mr. Rivers had started at the first of those musical accents, as if a
thunderbolt had split a cloud over his head, he stood yet at the close of the
sentence, in the same attitude in which the speaker had surprised him,
his arm resting on the gate, his face directed towards the west.
He turned at last with measured deliberation.
A vision, as it seemed to me, had risen at his side.
There appeared, within three feet of him, a form clad in pure white, a youthful,
graceful form, full, yet fine in contour, and when, after bending to caress Carlo,
it lifted up its head, and threw back a long veil.
They are bloomed under his glance a face of perfect beauty.
Perfect beauty is a strong expression, but I do not retrace or qualify it.
As sweet features as ever, the temperate climb of Albion moulded, as pure hues of
rows and lily, as ever her humid gales and vapoury skies generated and screened,
justified in this instance, the term.
No charm was wanting, no defect was perceptible.
The young girl had regular and delicate lineaments, eyes shaped and coloured,
as we see them in lovely pictures large and dark and full.
The long and shadowy eyelash which encircles a fine eye with so soft a fascination.
The penciled brow which gives such clearness, the white smooth forehead,
which adds such repose to the livelier beauties of tint and ray, the cheek oval,
fresh and smooth, the lips, fresh too, ruddy, healthy, sweetly formed,
the even and gleaming teeth without flaw, the small dimpled chin, the ornament of
rich, plentiest tresses, all advantages in short, which
combined, realised the ideal of beauty, were fully hers.
I wondered, as I looked at this fair creature, I admired her with my whole
heart, nature had surely formed her in a partial mood, and forgetting her usual
stinted stepmother doll of gifts, had endowed
this her darling, with a grand am's bounty.
What did Singen Rivers think of this earthly angel?
I naturally asked myself that question, as I saw him turn to her and look at her,
and as naturally I sought the answer to the inquiry in his countenance.
He had already withdrawn his eye from the Perry, and was
looking at a humble tuft of daisies which grew by the wicked.
A lovely evening, but late for you to be out alone, he said, as he crushed the
snowy heads of the closed flowers with his foot.
Oh, I only came home from... she mentioned the
name of a large town some 20 miles distant.
This afternoon.
Pappar told me you had opened your school, and that the new mistress was come,
and so I put on my bonnet after tea, and ran up the valley to see her.
This is she, pointing to me.
It is said Singen.
Do you think you shall like Morton?
She asked of me, with a direct and naive simplicity of tone and manner,
pleasing if childlike.
I hope I shall.
I have many inducements to do so.
Did you find your scholars as attentive as you expected?
Quite.
Do you like your house?
Very much.
Have I furnished it nicely?
Very nicely indeed.
And made a good choice of an attendant for you in Alice Wood.
You have indeed.
She is teachable and handy.
This, then, I thought, is Miss Oliver the Ares, favored, it
seems, in the gifts of fortune, as well as in those of nature.
What happy combination of the planets presided over her birth, I wonder.
I shall come up and help you to teach sometimes, she added.
It will be a change for me to visit you now and then.
And I like a change.
Mr. Rivers, I have been so gay during my stay at S.
Last night, or rather this morning, I was dancing till two o'clock.
The Wath Regiment a station there since the riots, and
the officers are the most agreeable men in the world.
They put all our young knife grinders and sysa merchants to shame.
It seemed to me that Mr. Syngen's underlip
protruded, and his upper lip curled a moment.
His mouth certainly looked a good deal compressed, and the lower part of his face
unusually stern and square, as the laughing girl gave him this information.
He lifted his gaze to from the daisies, and turned it on her.
An unsmiling, a searching, a meaning gaze it was.
She answered it, with a second laugh, and laughter well became her youth,
her roses, her dimples, her bright eyes.
As he stood, mute and grave, she again fell to caressing Carlo.
Poor Carlo loves me, said she.
He is not stern and distant to his friends, and if he could speak,
he would not be silent.
As she patted the dog's head, bending with native grace before his young and austere
master, I saw a glow rise to that master's face.
I saw his solemn eye melt with sudden fire, and flicker with resisteless emotion.
Flushed and kindled thus, he looked nearly as beautiful for a man as she,
for a woman.
His chest heaved once, as if his large heart, weary of despotic constriction,
had expanded, despite the will, and made a
vigorous bound for the attainment of liberty.
But he curbed it, I think, as a resolute rider would curb a rearing steed.
He responded neither by word nor movement to the gentle advances made him.
Papa says you never come to see us now, continued Miss Oliver, looking up.
You are quite a stranger at Vale Hall.
He has alone this evening, and not very well.
Will you return with me and visit him?
It is not a seasonable hour to intrude on Mr. Oliver, answered Syngen.
Not a seasonable hour, but I declare it is.
It is just the hour when Papa most wants company.
When the works are closed and he has no business to occupy him, now Mr.
Rivers, do come.
Why are you so very shy and so very somber?
She filled up the hiatus.
His silence left by a reply of her own.
I forgot, she exclaimed, shaking her beautiful curled head as if shocked at herself.
I am so giddy and thoughtless.
Do excuse me.
It had slipped my memory that you have good
reasons to be indisposed for joining in my chatter.
Diana and Mary have left you, and more house is shut up, and you are so lonely.
I am sure I pity you.
Do come and see Papa.
Not tonight, Ms. Rosamond.
Not tonight.
Mr. Syngen spoke almost like an automaton.
Himself only knew the effort it cost him thus to refuse.
Well, if you are so obstinate, I will leave you.
For I dare not stay any longer.
The dew begins to fall.
Good evening.
She held out her hand.
He just touched it.
Good evening, he repeated.
In a voice low and hollow as an echo.
She turned.
But in a moment returned.
Are you well?
She asked.
Well might she put the question.
His face was blanched as her gown.
Quite well, he enunciated.
And with a bow, he left the gate.
She went one way.
He another.
She turned twice to gaze after him as she tripped fairy light down the field.
He, as he strode firmly across, never turned at all.
This spectacle of another's suffering and sacrifice
wrapped my thoughts from exclusive meditation on my own.
Diana Rivers had designated her brother, inexorable as death.
She had not exaggerated.